FEDERICO MANZELLA

Symbolic Machine Learning Researcher



in federico-manzella-4586601a4 Federico-Manzella

(7) ferdiu

D 0000-0002-4944-2163



ABOUT ME

I am a Symbolic Machine Learning researcher at the ACL[AI] Lab at the University of Ferrara (Italy) since my first year of bachelor's degree in Computer Science. I contributed both in the theoretical and implementation part of algorithms for data analysis and machine learning and in the design and implementation of a framework for Symbolic Machine Learning in Julia programming language.

But my first love, and the reason I started studying computer science, is video Game Development. I started when I was 13, copying and modifying code around the web until I designed, developed and published various games on many digital distribution services.

I am looking forward to make these two worlds, the machine learning on the one hand and game development on the other, collapse into one.

EXPERIENCE

Symbolic Machine Learning Researcher **ACLAI (Applied Computational Logic and Artificial Intelligence)**

D 2021 - Ongoing



- research and study of transparent intelligent systems;
- research and study of feature selection methods;
- study of temporal data of physiological origin (EEG, ECG) and audio;
- design and development of a machine learning framework Sole.jl and study of unstructured data with symbolic methods in the Julia programming language.

Indie Game Developer and Designer

Month 2019 - Ongoing



- Book Hunter designed, developed and published a stealth adventure game on Steam;
- Thats Why You Always Lose Your Keys designed, developed and published an humorous strategic game on itch.io;
- Staring designed, developed and published an humorous puzzle game on itch.io;
- Poing Jump designed, developed and published an hyper casual game on Google Play Store;
- currently developing a platformer game based on pseudorealistic magnet physic using Godot 4 Game Engine (previously in Unity);
- currently developing a rhythm game for Android with Godot 4 Game Engine (based on the idea from a game developed for a Game Jam);
- currently designing and developing an online board game in Node.js.

MY LIFE PHILOSOPHY

"Behind every problem there is an opportunity." cit. Galileo Galilei

"The only way to go fast is to go well."

cit. Uncle Bob

STRENGTHS

Self-taught | Eye for detail Fast learner Problem solving

LANGUAGES

Italian **English** Spanish

EDUCATION

M.Sc. in Artificial Intelligence, Data Science and Big Data

University of Ferrara

Sept 2023 - Ongoing

Topics: artificial intelligence, machine learning, data analysis, computer vision, NLP.

B.Sc. in Computer Science **University of Ferrara**

Sept 2020 - March 2023

Grade: 109 / 110

Thesis: The Voice of COVID-19: Breath and Cough Recording Classification with Temporal Decision Trees and Random Forests Topics: computability and computational complexity, computer graphics, database, data structures, software engineering.

Advanced training course in Game Design and Development

ECIPAR Bologna

Nov 2019 - Dec 2020

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

- M. Coccagna, F. Manzella, S. Mazzacane, G. Pagliarini, V. Sironi, A. Gatti, E. Caselli e G. Sciavicco, "Towards an objective theory of subjective liking: A first step in understanding the sense of beauty," *Plos one*, vol. 18, n. 6, e0287513, 2023. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0287513.
- F. Manzella, G. Pagliarini, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "The voice of COVID-19: Breath and cough recording classification with temporal decision trees and random forests," *Artificial Intelligence in Medicine*, vol. 137, p. 102 486, 2023. DOI: 10.1016/J. ARTMED.2022.102486.

Conference Proceedings

- L. Balboni, M. Ghiotti, F. Manzella, M. Milella, G. Pagliarini, A. Paradiso, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "Third millennium symbolic learning with Sole.jl," in *Julia Programming Language Convention (JuliaCon 2023)*, 2023. indirizzo: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HTRhOmQIObg.
- P. Cavina, F. Manzella, G. Pagliarini, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "(Un)supervised Univariate Feature Extraction and Selection for Dimensional Data," in 2nd Italian Conference on Big Data and Data Science (ITADATA 2023), 2023.
- D. Del Fante, **F. Manzella**, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "Towards Symbolic Metaphor Identification," in *9th Italian Conference on Computational Linguistics (CLIC-IT 2023)*, 2023.
- M. Ghiotti, F. Manzella, G. Pagliarini, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "Evolutionary Explainable Rule Extraction from (Modal) Random Forests," in ECAI 2023 26th European Conference on Artificial Intelligence, September 30 October 4, 2023, Kraków, Poland Including 12th Conference on Prestigious Applications of Intelligent Systems (PAIS 2023), ser. Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence and Applications, vol. 372, IOS Press, 2023, pp. 827-834. DOI: 10.3233/FAIA230350.
- F. Manzella, G. Pagliarini, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "Efficient Modal Decision Trees," in 22nd International Conference of the Italian Association for Artificial Intelligence (AIXIA 2023), Springer Nature Switzerland, 2023, pp. 381–395. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-031-47546-7_26.
- M. Coccagna, F. Manzella, S. Mazzacane, G. Pagliarini e G. Sciavicco, "Statistical and Symbolic Neuroaesthetics Rules Extraction from EEG Signals," in Artificial Intelligence in Neuroscience: Affective Analysis and Health Applications 9th International Work-Conference on the Interplay Between Natural and Artificial Computation, IWINAC 2022, Puerto de la Cruz, Tenerife, Spain, May 31 June 3, 2022, Proceedings, Part I, ser. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol. 13258, Springer, 2022, pp. 536–546. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-031-06242-1_53.
- F. Manzella, G. Pagliarini, G. Sciavicco e I. E. Stan, "Interval Temporal Random Forests with an Application to COVID-19 Diagnosis," in 28th International Symposium on Temporal Representation and Reasoning, TIME 2021, September 27-29, 2021, Klagenfurt, Austria, ser. LIPIcs, vol. 206, Schloss Dagstuhl Leibniz-Zentrum für Informatik, 2021, 7:1–7:18. DOI: 10.4230/LIPICS.TIME.2021.7.

Topics: game design, level design, game development, game production, workflow organization (Slack, Git), C# programming language, Unity (game engine), Unreal Engine 4 (the basics), video games history.

DRIVER'S LICENSE

Car: B

PROGRAMMING

••••
••••
••••
••••
••••
••••
••••
••••
••••
••••

MY TOOLBOX

- OS: Fedora GNU/Linux.
- Editor/IDE: Kate/KDevelop, Atom/Pulsar, VS Code/VS Codium.
- Teamwork and Workflow: Git, GitHub, GitLab, Slack, Discord,
- Machine Learning: Sole.jl, MLJ, TensorFlow, Keras, scikit-learn.
- Game Engine: Godot 4, Unity, Unreal Engine.
- Audio Editing: Audacity, LMMS, FMOD, Wwise, Ardour 7, Guitar Pro 6/7/8, VCV Rack.
- Image Editing: GIMP, Adobe Photoshop, Krita, Inkscape, Aseprite, Spine.
- Database: MySQL, MongoDB.

MY HOBBIES

PROJECTS

Sole.jl

Dec 2020 - Ongoing

A framework for symbolic, transparent, and interpretable machine learning!

Godot Easing Functions

Feb 2020 - Ongoing

Bring the powerful easing functions to Godot Game Engine.

SimpleCaching.jl

Dec 2020 - Ongoing

A Julia package providing macros to cache result(s) of function calls

Ferdiu Engine

Feb 2023 - Ongoing

I'm building a Game Engine from scratch in C++. I started this project for Computer Graphics exam project but I was having so much fun while doing it that I decided to go further with it.

NVIDIA Optimus Tools for Linux

Jun 2020 - Ongoing

I developed, forked and trying to maintain as often as possible some tools to make it simple to use NVIDIA Optimus technology on Linux (mostly for Debian GNU/Linux), including:

- optimus-indicator: simple indicator for the system tray with Bumblebee and nvidia-xrun support;
- <u>nvidia-xrun</u>: utility to run separate X with discrete nvidia graphics with full performance;
- <u>nvrun</u>: makes the coexistence of bumblebee and nvidia-xrun comfortable.

Embedded Controller Tools for MSI Laptop for Linux

Sep 2022 - Ongoing

I developed, forked and trying to maintain as often as possible some tools to make up for the lack of tools for GNU/Linux systems to control the Embedded Controller of MSI laptops (e.g. *Dragon Center* and *MSI Center*), including:

- <u>isw</u>: Ice-Sealed Wyvern (forker to add support for MSI Katana GF66 12UG);
- <u>isw-indicator</u>: an Indicator app for my version of isw.

WWiser Launcher

🗖 Sep 2022 - Ongoing

A set of BASH and Python scripts for Linux which aims to replace the Wwise Launcher. This was achieved reverse-engineering the original launcher and the application protocol it use to fetch informations and assets from Audiokinetic servers.

SRTranslate

Jul 2021 - Ongoing

Translate a subtitles *.srt file to any language using Google Translate API. Before translating any line of the subtitle file, this application tries to join some adjacent lines to give the translator some context to outputs more accurate translations.

- music writer;
- play guitar (electric and acustic);
- play piano;
- home automation: Raspberry Pi;
- running;
- share my open-source with the community.

Autorizzo il trattamento dei miei dati personali presenti nel CV ai sensi dell'art. 13 d. lgs. 30 giugno 2003 n. 196 - "Codice in materia di protezione dei dati personali" e dell'art. 13 GDPR 679/16 - "Regolamento europeo sulla protezione dei dati personali".